hello and welcome everyone this is ACM
live stream
56.1 it's November 14th
2023 and we're continuing our discussion
series on these four papers by Alexander
aoria at all welcome to the active
inference Institute everyone we're a
participatory online Institute that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied Act of inference this is a
recorded and an archived and a published
live stream so please provide us
feedback so we can improve our work all
backgrounds and perspectives are welcome
and we'll follow video etiquette for
live streams head over to active
inference dorg to learn more about
projects and learning groups at The
Institute well today in
56.0 we're bringing out all of the four
Entre and we'll see where we go with
these big topics and with Alex here to
discuss so we'll begin with intros and
go from there so I'm Daniel I'm a
researcher in
California and what I would like to
explore in this stream beyond the trails
that were left in the zero is to get the
zoomed in what is the space of these
micro
motifs and then to compose those zooming
ins into the bigger picture what do
cognitive architectures look like in
2023 how is that different in theory and
in practice than
1983 and then where is this all heading
in terms of how we can do
useful and important research
blue cool thanks yeah I'm interested in
the 2043 cognitive architecture also um
and maybe exploring the space of uh
human cognitive architecture but also
like non-human cognitive architecture
and what that looks like and where maybe
that might take us um yeah that's good
Alex um all right uh yeah I'm Alex
Suburbia uh and I am the director of the
neural adaptive Computing laboratory and
uh computer science assistant faculty
Professor here at RIT in computer
science I'm also affiliate professor in
Psychology uh soon to be affiliate
professor in cognitive science and
affiliate faculty in computational
Neuroscience kind of a mouthful of
different involvements but I I do a lot
um yeah and uh I i' i' I've known about
the active INF inference Institute
before my some of my students are fans
of the channel already um so it's very
exciting to be here to talk to you guys
and I think that you have uh some really
good questions and I I think this uh set
of papers that you picked is a nice uh
little pathway through some of the
thinking that I've done over the years
uh what was funny when I was watching
the zero is uh and and again I also
noted this to uh both and Daniel and
email is that uh I thought oh there's
these other papers that I've written
that would have clarified or could have
so very easily this could have become
like a why don't you do 25 different
papers and you know I I I think that
might have become quite a burden but uh
uh some of my bonus slides that I I know
Daniel told me I didn't have to make any
or it's not typical but I have some
slides taken from some pieces of those
other papers that uh might have might
give some clarity uh to some pieces of
your guys questions depending on which
ones we start with uh and you know this
and the dot two of next week so again
thank you for having me this is very
exciting awesome I guess to begin how
did you get
into cognitive Sciences or cognitive
modeling oh okay the history the origin
story right uh yeah it's interesting so
when I without going into too much and
spending too much of the podcast on uh
one's own life story uh when I I I
started out in computer engineering or
computer science and engineering when I
was a young
undergraduate um and you know I even
came from like a background of Art and
Digital Arts which is kind of
interesting I had learned a program late
in high school um and uh then I'm
entering in uh Bucknell University was
where I went for my undergraduate
education and uh it was really strange I
did not do much I actually did not know
at all of machine learning let alone uh
cognitive models or computational
Neuroscience it was more of that strict
engineering education however uh I like
to think that something that I did which
was I'm a philosophy minor philosophy of
mind is what I studied I like to think
that's what biased me and kind of
launched me to where I am today uh so I
was always studying things like
Consciousness also ethics and other
aspects of philosophy in Greek
philosophy but uh philosophy of mind and
identity was something that sort of
motivated me to think well hey maybe
this stuff I'm doing in you know
hardware and Engineering I could combine
the two you know is there a way to sort
of emulate this concept of identity or
Consciousness um little did I even know
what you know the free energy principle
um and uh so then towards the end I
worked on complex adaptive systems again
nothing to do with machine learning uh
however it ties so beautifully
especially nowadays over the last year
I've done thinking uh and working with
Carl uh on the free energy principle and
aspects of the markup blanket it's funny
how all that construct ties back
together and it was like oh that stuff I
studied uh years ago wow it comes back
into Force full uh into play really
really strongly and then uh grad school
uh I was in uh Dr cely Gil lab who's
actually a very well-known information
retrieval scientist and a classical deep
learning researcher uh and uh and then I
was uh and he was more artificial
intelligence uh but that's the reason
why I got into deep learning he gave me
a survey I was exposed to neural Nets uh
he actually said to me years later the
reason he gave me that survey was to
discourage me from going into it but uh
uh he he told me he was glad that it
didn't work and then uh along the way uh
this is the part where I would the
cognition comes in I was co-advised by a
cognitive psychologist Dr David Ryder at
Penn State who uh also worked a lot with
another well-known cognitive scientist
Dr Frank Ritter who is he himself was
advised by Alan Newell and her Herbert
Simon so some of the greats of our time
in cognitive science and classical uh
artificial intelligence so I was in the
applied cognitive Sciences lab as well
and so between those two worlds uh I
think that's what sort of solidified me
to saying hey uh there's these big
problems in machine learning
particularly with credit assignment so I
don't know I'm pretty sure you guys are
familiar with these Concepts in one form
or another uh but credit assignment is
just like when we're doing back
propagation on a big neural network we
want to play the blame game how much
does this neuron contribute in a
positive or negative way to some cost
function and for some some reason uh
that always felt at odds with me because
along the way I worked with all kinds of
really non-mainstream models like
hopfield networks and Bolton machines
were actually my first loves if you will
uh that's what I did in my early PhD
thesis so that was at odds with what's
going on in deep learning even though
bols machines were used at the very
beginning and then everyone threw them
away um and so I think uh those ideas of
like memory consolidation and memory
storage and the fact that a hot field
Network couldn't remember everything
actually had very limited storage was
awesome to me and I was like I want to
probe that more uh can I build systems
with this and uh so I was one of the
early days working on boltzman machines
but like trying to sell them as the
thing we should care about um and then
towards the end of my PhD so now I'm
going to skip around a bit I did work on
recurrent neural Nets with Thomas
mikolov he's one of my friends uh and
then towards the end of my PhD uh I
I had somewhere along the line over the
years found predictive coding uh my my
joke to my grad students is Rish Rous
and Dana Ballard's classical 1990s paper
on predictive coding and classical
effects of the eye uh was something that
I I read so many times that I said I
slept with it under my pillow to hope
that I would absorb how incredible it
really was so that paper probably was
the strongest influence on why I decided
you know what for the rest of my life
I'm gonna do predictive coding I think
we need a lot of work here because it's
again also not a mainstream area it
resonated with some aspects of boltman
machines for me because I love iterative
processing uh and uh and I also read
parallel distributed processing by mlen
rumelhart Hinton uh Jeff back in the day
um so all all of those things kind of
sroll together and so that led me to
saying I want to do credit assignment
but in a biological way so
back props got to go it's clearly not
what the brain is doing I mean if it
turns out it does I'm I'm okay with
being wrong at least we explored some
other parts in the space that was beyond
backprop and so uh I do like the beian
brain Theory and the free energy
interpretations of predictive coding
this is why I'm a fan of aspects of
Carl's work um and so uh you know taking
that interpretation that came a little
bit later I would say once I so after
grad school or my PhD I uh got faculty
position at RIT um and that's where the
free energy principal sort of biased me
an active inference a little bit later
on actually most of my students in my
lab if at least two of them that promis
they would watch the stream they both
work on active inference so uh uh so we
talk a lot about that or read a lot of
these papers um and then of course very
recently have I finally gotten in touch
and uh and I collaborate now you know I
would say rather readily Now with uh
Chris Buckley who's well real really
well known in active inference Carl uh
in and free energy stuff um you know and
and and Rish Ral was on the survey so
it's really great the if I actually did
not give you in blue Daniel that big
survey uh that I recently worked with uh
Thomas so salvator and Anor mly but uh
we have this big review of predictive
coding over the last like three plus
decades and uh Carl's on there Rish
Row's on there Chris Buckley's on there
Thomas uh is on there so there's a lot
of really nice names and they're really
great people and it was crazy when I got
to talk to Rish Ral just as I told you
earlier I slept with under the pillow
with you know his 1990s nature paper so
to actually meet him in where meet him
in Zoom was rather incredible it was
actually it was a fun experience uh to
get to ask him even the questions I've
always had on the tip of my tongue and
so anyway that uh that sort of is what
molded me uh and uh the cognitive
science cognitive architecture part
which we'll talk about in point two um
that was heavily biased by David Ryder
and uh Frank Ritter and my discussions
with them and understanding
architectures like actar and sore which
are these older ones as you mentioned I
believe Daniel but or or blue like in
198 or in the 1980s and what's the
future uh and we can have some fun chats
about that as well um so yeah I would
say that because of that interesting
blend uh that sort of led me to say that
uh I'm not just the guy that says we got
to get rid of back propop and here's how
we do it and oh we let's use the beian
brain theory of predictive coding or
predictive processing to do that um but
rather uh let's use that but also let's
look to the common model of cognition
which is sort of like the grand Theory
or the blueprint theory in cognitive
science that I've also sold my soul to
uh I was just at uh DC a couple of weeks
ago at the uh cognitive science
Symposium one of the FSS symposiums for
triple AI uh and uh I was talking to
Andrea staco and John Lair and all the
greats from like the old cognitive
architectures or uh brain Imaging and
brain science and uh we were talking
about the directions where these go so
actually if we talk about later the
future of cognitive architectures might
I might bring in bring some of my
thoughts from that really really nice
Symposium and uh yeah and I could keep
blabbing I don't know if that really
completely answered your question as to
why but I guess too long didn't read
tldr uh cognitive science co-advisor and
grad school combined with an AI main
advisor in grad school philosophy of
Mind in my undergrad strongly biased me
with complex systems and I guess I'll
just blame boltzman machines because
honestly those were those were wonderful
wonderful and I still think elegant
little models that sort of like said we
got to look to things that don't do uh
don't work with at least gradients uh
with the reverse mode uh differentiation
algorithm that sort of characterizes
back
prop all the credit goes to boltzman in
the end
always oh and we should give Helm Holtz
some love too Bon Helotes and the helm
Holtz machines and you know those are
wonderful
too well blue if you want to begin with
a question or I'm happy to
ask there was a lot there so I I I could
follow up a few times but
um um I am interested in um what you
said about the hopfield network
forgetting and like how you thought that
that was perfect and like the most
exciting thing that it it didn't like
recollect perfectly the imperfect memory
um and I I think that that's interesting
to me also and that that kind of
introduces variance which we see like in
humans I I'm a very much like it's all
in your mind and like I I like to walk
the tight rope between like perception
and like reality and like what is
reality and um how how do you like when
you have a variant
um in a system like because it forgot X
Y or Z somewhere along the line how do
you find like the best variant best
variant like what would and then like
you know do you go on to selectively
refine like refining selective memory
and and what would that look like okay
so let me ask a clarification question
what do you mean by like variant model
or variant is in like a deviation that
that's maybe some ter
not quite it's not triggering something
so so like in bi in biology you get you
get variant right like so you have like
a biological variant but I mean just as
in humans like you have 25 people at a
party and 25 you have 25 different
perceptions and 25 different memories of
that party right and so so in when you
have like a network that forgets what do
you then do with that forgetting like
what you know you have 25 different
networks 25 different memories like how
do you select the best one or would you
want to and then how do you um like what
what do you think could be the outcome
of that why is that so exciting that you
have selective memory in a a
network okay um so I now I I understand
now what you're asking um to unpack that
a little bit briefly to answer why I
thought hopfield networks were so cool
or so exciting uh and just to make sure
that was clear was the fact that they
could only had like linear storage
capacity so as obviously you could
actually calculate I think it was even
there's in a formula with respect to the
dimensionality of the patterns you can
actually say how many memories I can
store Vector patterns especially binary
patterns yeah as I see the diagram being
pulled up here uh before things start to
getting corrupt so I think that that was
fascinating to me because uh I guess I
had assumed that you could just store
lots and lots and lots of information
these networks right and the fact that
memory can be corrupted uh it is a very
humanlike quality right we forget things
as you've brought up now blue in your in
your comments uh and I think it's a it
is a humanlike thing but it also
highlights and again it later I would
discover catastrophic forgetting in deep
neural networks which isn't really quite
at least in my view humanlike in the way
that it happens in machines where and by
the way for the audience that may may or
may not know catop forgetting it's like
you train on neural network on one task
to predict cats and dogs and then I move
on to airplanes and trucks and I learned
to predict that and then I say hey by
the way can you tell me if this is a cat
or dog and it it gets like zero percent
it just it's abysmal performance that's
not quite like a human because the joke
I tell also my students is um i' be like
oh as I learned to play the piano I
forget how to breathe uh that doesn't
quite work um so I think now tying that
back so that again is like motivation
and actually have like a bonus slide to
say like future directions this is like
one of the things that I've been working
to try to resolve uh with biological
models the hopfield network was
interesting in boltzman machines uh by
extension because they are just hop
field networks with Laten variables I
like the concept of attractors so when
you when you build like a hopfield
network you know the idea is that
because you're learning with contrastive
heavy and learning which was also the
algorithm that really caught my
attention I love that idea of just hey I
find equilibrium I run my model for like
a certain phase I compare it to some
clamped phase and then I just do a big
subtraction you get heavy en rules out
of it that's like one of the central
reasons to I liked heavy uh sorry
hopfield networks and boltzman models
but these idea of having these
attractors and space where if you could
figure out your optimization landscape
usually it's an energy landscape with a
a hot field model uh we are ping the
data let's say templates even or
representative aspects of data at these
little pins that are saying these points
in the energy landscape or what I'm
going to remember and patterns that look
similar so I guess this might kind of
slightly address your comment on a
variant so variant as in like variations
to particular memories if I meet someone
or I have certain attributes and a
vector this would fall into this
dynamical attractor right which again
would fall into this energy landscape I
really like that interpretation of how
memory works because then it's not just
me storing things in a heart array right
the idea of like let me just store every
Vector I've ever seen uh because now you
have this problem of capacity uh and
then again how do I build the and you
know there's some value in modeling
things in that way so this isn't a
criticism of any neural models in that
regard but I like the dynamical
attractor kind of point of view which
again then you can connect it nicely to
free energy and say oh it's your free
energy functional and I just walking
along my landscape to plot my memories
in there um so I think that's what
fascinated me was the energy based
interpretation uh and then again uh
boltzman machines and restricted
boltzman machines also known as
harmoniums uh they have this beautiful
kind of energy- based functional
interpretation and they too are
recollecting patterns right by this you
could say a dynamical reconstruction but
it's really just like I'm clamping noise
and I'm run running this until I reach
equilibrium and that sort of rep
retrieves from my memory some particular
element of life right some something
I've experienced in my Niche uh and I
pull out that attractor or I basically
am just saying how similar I am to that
attractor and then of course later on
there's been a lot of more efficient
work and then there's criticisms of bols
machines but um so I think like that's
particularly why I found them
specifically fascinating um I'm stop
myself there I don't know blue if that
was scratching at least that some type
of answer to your
question that was great thank
you earlier you mentioned this
Grand cognitive science framework kind
of the
general cognitive model so how do you
pursue that or where do we place or
enumerate all these features of diverse
intelligences like memory but clearly
just in your answer there's multiple
implementations that are nonoverlapping
of memory almost to the point where it's
like what what can you really say memory
even is so what are those core pieces
and how will we know or assess that we
have the relevant even um continents
sketched out for for worthwhile pursuit
of of anything other than just an
abstraction well I mean wonderful
question complex question and you know I
me I'm not the only person I mean I'm
just but one small voice right that you
know should speak to that I think all of
cogn all the great cognitive scientists
I've even just met in uh the short span
of my life uh have some interesting
differing thoughts so I think just to
clarify what you said Daniel the grand
kind of blueprint theory that I'm
referring to is actually well known
there's some nice papers I can try to
pass them on to you and blue if you
don't already know of them it's called
the common model of
cognition and uh by the way it is not
the only way you can build a mind uh
it's just the one that resonates the
most with me um and so I just want to
point that out it's not again just like
anything there's no such thing as a
silver bullet I would even venture to
say that there's probably a no free
lunch theorem that applies to cognitive
science just like I teach it in machine
learning uh so there's probably no one
cognitive architecture because I think I
think blue said it but you might have
said it Daniel about modeling things
that are not necessarily human uh which
I think could have generalize to animal
cognition but it could also even I was
my brain weirdly enough went to alien
cognition right things that are not even
of uh you know planet Earth maybe
there's other types of intelligent
organizations and I do believe that that
there is probably more than one way to
build an an intelligent computational
entity but with without getting into
that also potential can of worms um the
common model of cognition I think to
sketch out what you said lays out the
continents of the mind to use your word
uh the reason I like it is that it sort
of is like a synthesis the when you read
the paper uh they themselves at the time
this was now years ago that the original
common model of cognition uh paper view
paper came out and they looked at things
like actar SAR
Sigma I don't know if they looked at
like for example they might have looked
at versions of Randall O'Reilly's work
he does a lot of really nice stuff like
Libra the Libra architecture I don't
remember if that was in there um and
other variants of course I don't think
they had uh like Chris Elias Smith's
group at waterl who does who did the
work on spawn you might have heard of
nango which are like spiking nural model
toolkits uh spais and Spa Daniel if you
want to write that that way because
there's like a science paper that he had
years ago that came out about spawn um
but they looked at maybe not those
specifically those would be like the
updates uh but they looked at
particularly the first three that you
have in your uh in your notes there and
they they synthesiz these architect said
what are commonalities here what are
they trying to model um and I I
sometimes I misuse the word brain
regions but rather it's more like
functional uh continents I'm going to
borrow your terminology Daniel of the
brain and they kind of chop it up into
saying well what are the grand pieces of
computation that goes on and let's see
if I can distill it from my own limited
memory uh you know we have our motor
functionality our motor cortex we have
perception uh and of course now I of
course have added my own addendums to
that where you could break up perception
into modalities like audio visual uh and
then of course all Factory and touch and
taste and all these other elements
elements that maybe we don't model very
well but we'll leave that again also as
a separate discussion and then the parts
of memory so we have for example
procedural memory then we have
declarative memory and we have working
memory and those are kind of like the
big big kind of groupings of all the
other things inside of there there's
different types of memory that you could
start partitioning up um and so like
declarative memory would be like
fact-based knowledge or world-based
knowledge could also include episodic
memory which is kind of blobbed into
there uh and I've done some work on
modeling episodic memory because I do
things with active inference as apply to
reinforcement learning so of course you
need you know at least a a type of
Replay memory to sort of refresh your
you know statistics I'll leave that
vague for now and then you have working
memory which are again this could be a
bias on my end because I have studied
things like actar but they're like
buffers so I think of working memory as
not just this one module but rather many
little tiny occurrences of this module
and they are the glue that helps
transmit information between various
continents in the brain and then we have
procedural memory and procedural memory
is really interesting to me and I think
it resonates really strongly with just
because again we're you're the active
inference Institute and I have done
research in active inference so uh
because I remember a question you had
Daniel on point Zer you said where's the
action uh then later you guys answer
that question actually but uh just to be
clear there's other papers too where I
try to show you how to do active
inference without even a cognitive
architecture with predictive coding if I
ever show you these bonus slides we
could look at some of that but um anyway
and uh procedural memory I think
resonates really nicely with active
inference in the sense that I put in
there it's dumic model so again if we
imagine we have perception and we think
of that as you know the context of
active inference which is usually a PDP
partially observable Markoff decision
process uh let's assume that marvian
assumptions are okay for now I I have
criticisms of that but the idea is that
we have our input space we have a latent
space that's what uh your cores are
doing right like the visual cortex is
transforming beams of light or pixels in
a computer into some distributed
neuronal representation ideally very
sparse and this is again I know blue is
very interested in uh my uh my aspects
of sparsity which is something I'm
obsessed with uh and I think we all
should be obsessed with because that's
very biological uh and then uh if we put
the motor cortex as like well it's going
to take other signals and that's where
the action comes in Daniel so like for
example motor cortex is GNA take
information from probably information
processed in the cortices maybe
information queried from various pieces
of memory uh transferred to the working
memory and then they'll do something and
then we'll get our our signals whether
they come from another part of the brain
like the prior preference part of the
brain which is kind of like our you know
uh goal oriented signals uh and then the
part that again to go back to the
procedural memory the Dynamics model
that lives in there the way that I've
been modeling it and I do this in COG
engine but also I just do this in my
robotics work too
uh is that that's kind of living in
latent space is trying to guess the next
state the sparse distributed state of
predictive coding circuitry and with
that it's saying oh I'm wrong uh you get
the basis of an epistemic signal right
and that's how you encourage foraging
right because exploration is like to me
my view is the Su the real Crux of
active inference if you don't have
foraging you don't have this uh
epistemic kind of signal to drive you to
be curious about the world I uh you know
I know you guys have talked about
curiosity um but also the uh prior
preference in obviously plays a role
because you could either incode goals
and if we're doing RL we sort of do it
like oh well we could use the reward
function or maybe we train some prior
model but uh the other way to look at
that is that's where also like
homeostatic constraints could be uh you
know embodied uh and that's the stuff
I'm doing with Carl now I'm G to have a
a nice big paper that's about to come
out once I finish applying some of his
edits and it'll basically address that
the the life aspect of this but put that
aside uh because it's another can of
worms lots of can of worms to avoid um
and then the last piece of this puzzle
is inside procedural memory uh there's
the basil ganglia which is another
structure I'm very obsessed with uh that
in the prefrontal cortex and these
particular constructs in the brain uh
they do many things I mean the basil
gangle is often you know uh you know
cited and studied for like dopamine
application and reward injection uh
that's where the reward signals come and
you know I've often used that
interpretation but another thing and
this is why uh Andrea staco who's at the
Symposium and I really enjoy talking to
him has done a lot of study of the basil
ganglia he has put in his work and he
has found neuroscientific evidence of it
being like an information routing system
and that to me is a
humongous uh tool for tackling
catastrophic forgetting because the way
I see it is if I have this neural
structure that is responsible for
deciding what task I'm in the brain or
what pieces of information should play a
role in the task that I am doing uh it's
like suppressing regions of neurons and
exciting other regions so it also
induces sparsity to tie back to varsity
at the the the most extreme level right
it's like turning off parts of your
brain and saying this is Task dependent
and the prefrontal cortex can be argued
to do some of this too I haven't modeled
that specifically but I've seen other
people do that uh but again the basil
gangalay was one thing and so I have
work on that that you guys aren't also
talking about but again I've already
thrown too many papers at you but uh
focusing on just like oh can I do
information routing with some basic
predictive coding circuitry um so I
think that that sort of big glut of uh
of speech that I just threw at you guys
sort of gives you an answer Daniel as to
like how you would why the common model
of cognition uh is so nice is what I
just explained was uh I just used their
blueprint I mean they didn't say the the
the mechanics and the active inference
part that's my twist to it right oh can
I reinterpret com model of cognition
through free energy the answer is well
I've bet everything I have on that idea
um and then you know and I teamed up
with someone Mary Kelly at Carlton
University uh and she works on for
example uh manura 2 memory and Hyper
Vector symbolic structures and
holographic memory and Hyper vectors and
that's where even though I know uh hot
field Nets that's kind of another world
that you know they sort of intersect so
we we put that in there too but I don't
you know that's maybe we should save
some stuff for point two um but uh the
what I what I just explained is I walked
you through the blueprint which was very
vague it just said we should have these
Grand continents uh and they might do
certain things they have like little
arrows in their diagram about
information that's transferred what
modulation is going on uh but then they
leave the implementation level kind of
vag right the ideaas it could be
whatever you want you could implement it
even classically like in the 1980s with
you know production systems and if then
statements yeah this is a good diagram
actually um you know yeah you can kind
of see all some of the key aspects of
memory here uh and again too what's nice
I took from common model of cognition
and uh I do have a slide here I keep
saying I have a slide maybe I'll show
you one just so I can prove to the
audience I do have them uh you know the
idea is that the action element the
active aspect of active inference common
model cognition also speaks to right it
says well we have to have a motor cortex
uh it doesn't tell you what to do with
that motor cortex except that it's going
to you know produce some motor command
and then you know it will transmit to
the body uh and will leave embodiment as
another thing that's another can of
worms that I have been trying to address
and inactiv ISM which is your Niche and
how that relates to this but let's just
zoom in on the the the architecture of
the mind and it has all these components
so the way I Envision the future just to
tie this to another question to make
sure that I'm not just blabbing but
keeping us you know uh you know useful
uh is that I think the direction we're
gonna head or should head I don't know
if everyone else will follow that is
that you want to build these biological
cognitive architectures um rather than
just okay you know let's rely on a
production system like we do an act art
which is valuable I have it's not really
a criticism of that because maybe the
level of modeling you want to do is I
want to encode this knowledge it's a lot
more intuitive sometimes to encode in
like if then statements and logical
statements as you did in classical
architectures you can interpret it
easier um but the part I think that uh
we really need to push for is how do we
get that type of behavior that type of
self-organization uh without me
hardcoding this knowledge right because
again it gets to expert systems and good
oldfashioned AI uh we kind of don't want
to be doing that we want to say can we
do this in a neural way and then uh the
answer I try to jump ahead to is I say
by the way don't do back propop because
while you could do back propop and
there's I think work on people trying to
build types of cognitive architectures
with that at least it's a better step
than uh you know chat gbt and claiming
that that solves cognition because it
doesn't uh and I I am in that camp
uh but we again leave that can of worms
somewhere else but the idea is that you
skip that and go into something that's
biological which is predictive coding uh
there are other things you can do I
actually am working on other things
besides predictive coding uh maybe we
can chat about that in future directions
if that question comes up um but I think
predictive coding and predictive
processing offer you a lot uh that you
know other algorithms right now might or
might not give give you they might have
drawbacks um and this could even help
answer if the question comes up Daniel
if you're interested like uh what
aspects of neurobiology does that bring
to the table but I also think it has uh
the best way to convince machine
learning individuals is to explain the
Practical elements of it uh because you
know a lot of times they'll say well who
cares about modeling the brain I just
want to build an intelligent system um
but you can you can use predictive
coding and predictive processing as
pragmatic uh type of argument and you
can say hey well you get this you get
this you get this and uh among those
arguments is sparsity but there's
there's even more powerful pieces that
we could go into I think I'm gonna stop
now because that's a lot of information
I don't know if if I missed any piece of
your
question no it's great I'll ask a short
question from the chat VI writes can we
represent declarative memory with neural
network-based technique such as hot
Field
net was it did you say Viet yes that's
my I believe that's my one of my
students um so uh yeah he's also works
on active inference as well so uh I'm
not surprised that he would throw a
question like that um the answer is yes
uh uh you can actually there's a lot of
good work already even without the
cognitive architecture kind of structure
because again think of the common model
cognition is like a blueprint that tells
you what things you're going to need to
have and how they interact but if you
zoom in on one of those continents
declarative memory as was pointed out in
the question uh for example you can use
Vector symbolic structures you can use
for example Manu manura 2 memory uh
there's a lot better I would recommend
faster models which are heavan based
systems right you can model heavan
memory uh associative memory hetero I
ative memory with a lot of these like
simple kind of heavy andlike constructs
the learning is very efficient as well
uh they don't come without the drawbacks
but um so the answer is yes and you can
model them with I think heavy in
networks uh heavy in learning which is a
correlational local learning rule uh the
other part with the hopfield network you
can also do that and it's weird
because while uh the work I have
currently done said we will do h field
networks in our cognitive architecture
which we'll probably chat more about
that in point to Cog engine uh but we do
have plans to do like uh what do you
call it modern hopfield networks that's
a particular uh instantiation of
hopfield Nets that is actually very uh
efficiently implementable uh as I've
discussed with my collaborator Mary and
uh and others like Robert West at
carlston uh you know talking about these
types of things but uh you can use a hot
field Network to sort of use uh to
create that dynamical attractor
interpretation I was telling blue about
earlier uh the idea is that you know
it'll have a certain capacity but the
problem is is we need to make sure that
we have enough capacity because again uh
I don't think I ever completely properly
answered Blue's question about variance
or you know differences between what's
you know reality versus what you think
reality is and there's some interesting
connections to predictive coding that
also answer that question um but um the
idea is that if you have you know one
single hot field Network that might not
be enough but I imagine chaining a bunch
of these together to create what I call
an assembly or an assembl to use one of
Carl's words AIDS of hot field Nets I
think is one way to build uh a
completely neural implementation of
declarative memory uh another piece of
declarative memory that we did model
I won't argue it was the most efficient
thing you should do uh but it can be
done is manura 2 uh and again that you
can look it up it's Hinman and all and
uh hinman's old work it's a heavy and
it's an approximation of a large heavy
End Auto associative memory and uh what
we did is we modeled the episodic memory
with like a big manura 2 the reason I
say it's not a good idea is manura 2 is
really slow because it's kind of like
approximating this heavan associativity
with like a weird Echo query style
lookup table uh at least the
implementation and even when you
vectorize it and put it in tensorflow or
you know your favorite linear algebra
back end uh you can only get so much of
a speed up so for very big memories I
don't think that's the right place to do
it but the value of what we did is we
essentially try to emulate what episodic
memory does when you do replay and
reinforcement learning right so uh you
have to do some weird hacks to make uh
the uh episodic memory predict the next
thing rather than recall this thing from
a corrupted input Vector that's called
heter associative memory uh and we did
some things with like a window and we
said hey have this predict the next
sensory or sorry Laton Vector since you
know I told you we live in Laten space
in uh the cognitive architecture uh
maybe predict what you thought the
original Act you're taking and the
reward and we sort of use that to roll
out little streams or mini streams of
episodes uh and then we use that to
train the modules that are inside the
cognitive architecture for example if
you do replay you can refresh the
Dynamics model you can refresh the motor
cortex because again you're querying
this episodic declarative memory to say
hey remember these little tiny mini
experiences um the other problem with
manura 2 was that all you can only
remember so far into the future so it
gets a little wonky and hacky when you
try to build like these like little
lookup windows but there are better
memories out there and I actually my
cabber and I have talked about using
modern hot field networks as one
possible uh construct and they're very
cleanly implementable they almost look
like Auto encoders which is kind of
crazy uh at least from like the
engineering point of view and so once
you understand that you're like oh I
could build all of these and build again
what I said earlier assembl loids right
or Assemblies of uh these hot field
Network structures right and maybe see
what those do uh when I want to recall
particular pieces of experience so that
would be the answer to your question uh
I would say I only have some experience
with the episodic piece of declarative
when it comes to like the world fact
graph organizational knowledge I don't
have much to say yet I know you can use
use manura 2 and Vector symbolic and
holographic memory and hot field memory
to emulate that people have done that on
like for example language tasks um
another really nice name and he's done
work on I don't know if you guys in the
active inference Institute know him Ben
Gerel he's you know a premier researcher
in okay you know Ben I see you shaking
you know an AGI right and he has open
Cog and I know that he's done some
really nice work on graphs knowledge
graphs and there's people that have had
discussions with him about neural
implementations of that because when he
and I have talked and I I also work a
bit with him too uh I've said to him you
know okay what what would be the like
purely neural version of this and there
are ways to do it whether it's
simulatable uh in our you know Computing
systems nowadays I don't know it it can
be expensive but it can be done so he
would be open Cog might provide a nicer
cleaner answer than I possibly could
today about like the world fact
knowledge in graph organization of how
we think about Concepts uh and you know
and I think open Cog has some of that
answer uh but again I'm gonna speak with
that as the final statement and boundary
of my knowledge and you know let the
audience look into that but I do
recommend Ben gertel's work in that area
too so Robert West Ben gzel these are
some really nice names kind of look at
how they either use the common model of
cognition or they build their own
cognitive architecture and they model
certain pieces of this
structure uh that have nothing to do
with let's say predictive coding because
Ben the reason he's working with me is
because I've said oh we should do it
with predictive coding and he was like
that's a great idea uh and so you know
hence collaborations get born but U so
yeah and obviously and as Daniel's
writing that statement you'll notice I'm
extremely uh biased
but I think with rather good reasoning
uh even from a neuroscientific point of
view there's a lot more evidence for
predictive coding than there is for back
propop in the brain plus you can
approximate back propop with predictive
coding if you squint at it and make the
right theoretical assumptions in the
right way so uh obviously I'm going to
say everything should be built with
predictive coding um and then also the
beautiful thing and I Know Carl will
like this if he ever watches this is uh
you know then you can also State it's uh
it's optimizing or minimizing a
variational free energy and we can
derive where that comes from and it's a
it's a beian model right and so you have
this basian graphical model
interpretation uh it's a really really
elegant framework too so that's another
strength I think of predictive coding I
guess I am the market man for it now but
uh but I I I really do believe in it and
uh it's it's served me well over the
last I mean I'm coming up on almost
almost a if we count grad school almost
on a decade of working on on this and uh
and I do think predictive coding is at
the Forefront of where we need to go uh
if we want you know biological humanlike
even uh machine
intelligence and I'm gonna stop there
too because I don't know if there's more
questions I can keep going very
easily yeah it's awesome very um
encouraging certainly you lay it out
differently everyone does but you lay it
out very
differently it's actually very rare to
start on a high road it's not exactly
the high road laid out by the free
energy principle but this kind of
approach to cognitive science which is
like let's sketch out the
functionalities and then drill in that's
how a big tent is built because it
clarifies that there's all these
different implement ment ational
techniques none of which can be all
things in all settings and then another
another piece that that the work holds
up is what's
biological when after all the neural
network is the great great great
grandchild already of a cell type and so
what what is modern and biological and
then it just made me think about how
there's the pure
biomimicry which is usually like if
somebody were actually interested in
studying that system to resolve some
pathology or just to do natural history
and that's one sense that we might be
doing biologically inspired computation
but whether it's leaving the door open
to our alien colleagues or developing
new synthetic intelligences we need
something that's both biological but
also novel and then this leads to
consideration of well what are the
fundamental constraints other than the
histor vity of the life forms today with
two wings or six legs or whatever they
may be what are the real features and
that's where we complement those
fundamental attributes identified by the
common cognitive model like memory
action selection and perception where
those come together with like local
processing
only and then also some more potentially
aspirational things like low energy
compute and other
features so these are just some big
topics and it's kind of
like come work on it these are the
challenges because they're laid out the
challenges are not esoteric at
all oh we've either known about some of
them for a while and just never resolve
them or or they're becoming more
pressing in today's day and age like you
brought up the energy compute part right
and Energy Efficiency and you know we
global warming regardless of whether or
not you want to you know accept it is is
upon us uh and uh we have the problems
of even even in AI there's this thing
called Green AI versus red Ai and I've
written a little bit about this in some
of my papers as a motivation uh to
looking to biology because you know the
brain is regardless of its you know own
limitations every biological system has
you know trade-offs that it has to make
but uh it is an extremely energy
efficient system and it's an example of
beautiful parallelism uh as well as low
energy compute and if we could get even
just a little bit of that in our systems
today that would be huge so I think
that's a nice uh motivation of course I
also work in well I know you guys talked
about one of my papers spiking neuron
Nets which gets us into neuromorphics
and neuromorphic Computing uh and I
think there's a lot of really nice
Hardware uh in silico that's out there
that we could take advantage of uh but
the key is finding the right
algorithms that we could Implement there
uh and carry over the best of all the
worlds right the best principles uh that
our software simulations and
mathematical arguments make uh but then
instantiate them in you know you know
let's say a memoris crossbar uh and you
know and I've worked and talked with
different people uh including Intel's Lo
ship you know and I'm not saying that
that there's many different ways you can
build these constructs and and I know
that because I've I've watched some of
Carl's chats with you guys and talked
with Carl about this is also I do think
the biological chimeric implementations
is like a really cool area I'm a huge
fan of uh organoids and uh and organoid
intelligence I I think that that's a
humongous Place uh that's like a new
frontier almost uh given like smirnov's
work and a couple other people and uh I
think that's where like these ideas of
predictive coding and the computational
models we build are valuable to even
consider in these biological systems
either study them and see do they match
back to my mathematical theoretical
predictions or can we manipulate or
engineer them to you know maybe induce
similar kinds of compute uh or maybe
we'll just see that it pops out maybe
they're just doing predictive coding and
we're going to see that the neuronal
structures emerge and I think that would
be fascinating uh a quick point I want
to add and because I see blue raising
her hand so I just want to mention that
the thing I like about my interpretation
of predictive coding and it's not only
my own it's just that I carry that
forward is predictive coding as I've
talked to people is interpreted in a lot
of different ways like in Psychology
predictive coding kind of has
similarities but it's not quite where I
work which is the mechanis IC version of
predictive coding and it's interesting I
think you can borrow those worlds like
hey the the idea of predicting error and
feeding that back in or matching
discrepancies you know in our memories
you know that's a beautiful concept and
that's you know what psychologists look
at cognitive scientists kind of see
things in that way um biologists and
neurobiologists might sometimes talk
about predictive coding but they they
might not necessarily mean it like in
the concrete ways that uh my work which
was inspired you know by Regis Rous and
others uh you know to say let me build
you the exact mechanics and the Dynamics
and I think that's important to get
right uh I am even though recently I'm
getting a little more philosophical
which I love and theoretical uh and in
talking to Carl and others and Ben uh
there's this engineer in me that cannot
divorce away the very specific Dynamics
and the not just the mathematical like
oh the ordinary differential equations
but how does that get implemented
efficiently because I think that's what
lies in the future is the marriage of
these kind of highlevel theoretical
mathematical philosophical Concepts
their mechanistic description which is
what like predictive coding says hey one
set of neurons tries to get another set
of neurons firing rates or their
activities and we can feed that back in
and you can repeat this Motif and build
very
beautiful constructs like what I try to
do in cognitive architectures or little
PVP systems and then we also have the
spikes right how does that compute
happen at this very fine grein level and
then how does that get put onto a chip
and then I think the other piece that
then I'll shut up is uh the connection
to the niche uh I think it goes back to
the body and you can't ignore the body
and I have a lot more to say about that
that but I'm going to bite my tongue for
a little bit because I want you guys to
read that paper maybe we'll have another
chat in the future about it uh Carl and
I have really thought very deeply about
this the role of the body and that has
nothing to do sometimes with neurons or
at least not the neurons that we model
and then the niche itself and how does
that have a role and then I know you can
go into and I know all the cognitive
theories like extended cognition
embedded cognition how do other agents
and cultures and tools play a role
uh the extended uh theory of mind
because I I I did study that as a
philosopher so I think like all those
parts are gonna those all need to be
reconciled and build this kind of
framework and I think Daniel you're
right you can use blueprints like the
CMC as a stepping stone and I think that
that top down way is a nice way but then
you also merge it right with all this
bottom up it's it's kind of like you're
doing predictive coding but in the
scientific realm right you have this top
down kind of Direction you want to fill
but then you have all this mechanical
low-level stuff that you really can't
ignore if you want like Energy
Efficiency and where do they meet in the
middle so it's a bottom up top down
which is beautiful because it it repeats
the the metaphor of biology and I'll
stop because I see blue it's time to let
someone else
speak you did
it so you really like stole my thunder
there oh sorry about that I have a lot
to say sometimes it's okay no no it's
perfect so I really wanted to ask about
the role of the niche and especially
like in when we're talking about like
Energy Efficiency and predictive coding
and the compute power Etc like I think
about um like what makes us efficiently
able to do cognition and it really is
like cognitive offloading into the niche
like the internet the phone like click
click click now I know this right and
then even like with non-human systems
like ants like leaving pherone traces in
the environment that convey a ton of
information as to where to go and what
to do and so how can we then bring the
efficiency of cognitive AR Co cognitive
offloading into cognitive architectures
that we can then leverage for increased
compute power with very little um you
know effort on in terms of like the
actual
compute so the answer to your question
is extremely hard right it's a Grand
Challenge if you will um I would say
that the right path and I these things
are okay for me to share because
thankfully uh they're not all of my
invention uh
so to think about how other agents and
other tools could be efficiently used to
allow our own agents right our
artificial agents to achieve their tasks
you do need to now finally answer the
question of the body and the question of
the environment and I've been thinking a
lot about this and let's just assume
that you can simulate it that's another
issue and of itself but you pick your
world right so let's say I'm going to so
okay actually I'll pick I'm gonna start
with my body I'm gonna do a quadruped
robot right like you know what is it big
dog or spot right the little robots that
are out there and that's going to be my
my actual morphological construct the
body in which that I'm going to
manipulate it now that body let's assume
that I have access to all aspects of its
physical mechanics okay and it's
artificial hardcoded routines because
robotics have a lot of like automated
procedures like you're not going to
necessarily need to manipulate every
piece of the arm you know you're going
to use like take advantage of inverse
kinematics and other algorithms that
allow you to say I just need to move
this point and the rest of the arm will
kind of coordinate around that and that
is an offload of what the neurons need
to do or the neural compute let's say
organized and I'm a fan of common mod
cognition so let's assume you build your
little brain from the CMC point of view
that's going to again not worry that
much about the fine grain mechanics of
the pieces of let's say the quadrupeds
front right arm right or front left arm
it's going to offload because it knows
that as long as I tell you I plan to
move this piece of my you know I don't
know joint in this direction the rest of
the arm is going to fall along you've
already now done embodiment which is
embodied cognition which says the and
I'm I'm on the extreme end there's like
spectrums I've studied in cognitive
science uh there's uh the body kind of
influences the mind then there's
isolated cognition brain and EV that and
then there's really strong embodiment
which is the body does a lot and the
Brain kind of just says hey let me send
you a little control signals to
manipulate you so that's the embodiment
now we get to the niche and by the way
so I've already started to answer your
question because I picked a body you're
going to need to commit yourself to a
construct which by the way means you're
not as general as you would want to be
but it gets you a chance to answer the
question because now you say quadruped
now you say what's the niche where is
that quadruped going to operate and I
don't know I'm gonna pick something
really simple uh outside my office
there's you know some hills and some
grass and some trees
uh and I'm going to specify this little
world uh maybe I going to design some
way of recharging that robot's batteries
you know because obviously we need to
create some type of Life Giving Force
some resources uh for this to look for
and I specify other properties of my
environment now I've specified my Niche
now I've answered concretely the exact
world that my quadrip is going to
operate so now I know the inactive
cognition comes into play right because
now I have to interact with the physics
of my world it's going to manipulate the
robot it's going to damage the robot the
robot's going to have to respond to this
uh so remember under the hood is like a
CMC neural predictive kind of neural
construct it's offloading a lot of its
cognition to the body the body says oh
I'm going to also take advantage of
sensors that I can read in my
environment I know like I don't want to
be maybe in a very hot area that starts
to you know interact badly with certain
properties of the robotic construct and
then to now get at the answer to what
you said about other things well in this
world I should also and I I think
there's some work in I cited it in the
one paper that's going to come out uh uh
about uh like tools you have to specify
what are objects that are manipulable so
you need to Define your affordances and
by the way this is again defining the
niche I think it's really important not
to just say oh I'm going to throw it in
any environment and we'll just it'll
work somehow you need to define the
properties of your Niche to some degree
because that's how we can also
experimentally analyze and and study
what's going on and you say what are the
affordances what are things that I can
do what properties of environment am I
able to manipulate that I let's say even
want to that could help you model this
uh and then you introduce other quadrip
heads with the same exact underlying
cognitive structure because let's say
we're not going to do
heterogenous uh
multi-agent system so you know I
introduced a couple other spots right
which are also operating under the same
principles they minimize a variational
free energy inside the common model of
cognition they have the same you know
roughly uh you know artificial dynamics
that they can offload to their robot
bodies and they could work together
right they could create herds right they
could have herd Behavior or group
Behavior because maybe now they're going
to find those Port charges or whatever
the resources is that I allow them maybe
there's maybe they're solar powered I
don't know and they have solar panels
and they need to collect from the
sunlight but obviously if it rains they
need to hide and so you can now say
those Dynamics those groups now they
interact maybe one of the spot Bots
found a good area and this is a really
good place to exploit their prior
preference which is you know to survive
hey I Want More Energy I need to just
continue living right because I think
life is the the place you have to look
uh they they don't want to die they
don't want to terminate so they're going
to work together to do that so that
answers the embedded part right because
the embedded aspect of it is the
cultural and this is an approximation
I'm not g to claim that a a a little
herd of quadruped spot Bots right are
going to have a society I I I don't know
that's an emergent property perhaps but
they'll have some means of communication
and that way allows them to organize
themselves as their own little system
you know in their Niche and then of
course because we specified the
affordances and properties in the
environment that you can manipulate you
have extended cognition right because
these tools allow them to better survive
better find those areas that for example
allow them to charge their batteries or
you know collect Sun at the right times
and avoid damage from the world you know
when it's raining or when there's
inclement weather and again I'm kind of
like vaguely describing a very Comm
complex Niche you could really
experimentally control it maybe make it
a lab and you know you have artificial
blocks and charging ports and maybe you
could kind of simplify this a little bit
but I think that's where that doesn't
like give you the exact answer because
you know if I had the exact answer I
probably would have implemented it and
we would have solved AGI right but I do
think that's the pathway to answering
your question right it says if you want
to even have a chance scratching at the
answer of
efficient uh uh interactions with the
environment using objects and tools to
solve problems and offload your
cognition to these uh let's say
non-neural non-biological entities or
these non-living or non uh let's say
planning entities I Know Carl talked to
you guys long ago about the difference
between like well the environment's also
its own system uh but it doesn't plan
but it's you know subject two
thermodynamic constraints and the en and
the uh entity itself is also you know
that one is different because it can
plan so there's like a little bit of
like you know its own ability to change
it act outcomes with planning his
inference um so you could kind of like
use that as your starting point to say I
need to define the niche I need to
define the body then I need to define
the organization of the brain structure
that goes into that body because you you
do need to have the neural part we're
gonna if we're interested in modeling
let's say very high level cognition and
behavior and how does that interact with
the hardware and that's another question
and of itself that you know I'm I've
been thinking about and I think with all
of that you get a chance to now simulate
do experiments uh and actually see how
does that efficient interaction emerge
right what can we study aspects of
embedded cognition right into this
little uh experimental Niche and agent
niche and Collective agent Niche setup
that I've constructed so I think that's
like an interesting place that I would
this is where I would go right and I'd
love to go if I had resources but uh you
know these are that I think that gives
you a chance to begin to answer that
question and then it will tell you
what's wrong with a lot of things too
because I think it'll say you're you're
GNA quickly especially if you just even
pick the body and you're doing ody
cognition you say uh hey wait a minute
this neural construct let's see back
propop right uh it isn't working very
well right because why I need to unroll
in time I need a time machine to do back
propop with time based data um but
predictive coding doesn't really need
that right oh probably that might be the
right neural structure for the brain uh
because now it interacts with my robot
Hardware which has very limited
resources you have very limited memory
and compute that you can run with so
already there you've now manipulated
your software you have now
co-designed the hardware and the softare
where a little bit to interact in the
context of this morphological construct
your body and because you've you've also
Define where it's going to operate you
also understand what properties of the
environment you need to be aware of
maybe you can build that as an inductive
bias into the system because we don't
want to play Evolution because that's
usually how you emerge these systems but
I don't know if I want to wait doing
genetic algorithms for you know whatever
simulated thousands and thousands of
years so maybe we need to build those
inductive biases as well and that's
another interesting research area and I
think now I'm I'm digressing so I'm
gonna stop
there it's great again
again sorry oh just the the pathway is
clear and in fact this is even in some
ways an
anti-reductionist pathway that actually
starts from the bigger context you
stepped through specification of the
niche in the context
getting to the embodiment including the
extended embodiment phermones and all of
this with a niche like each time you
step through then to the brain and the
body then into the multi-agent and then
that is where the evolutionary and the
ecological Dynamics kick into play Eco
evoo is going to pick up once there's
like a population even if it's an in
silico population that has resource
constraints or it actually is a
materialized system um
then the ball's rolling and it either
persists or
doesn't it's like a landing strip for
our efforts and and a organizing
principle for our research whether we're
like just beginning to do cognitive
science research and thinking about
going to grad school or something or
trying to recap on this flurry of
development over the last years of being
aware for a long
time um it's actually a to me a mark of
the advancement not just like how fast
or performant the systems are but how
many index card
type agreements or ways of coordinating
that we have we have the common model we
have of course AC infant free energy
principle which we've barely talked upon
we have this kind of General agreement
of the
structuring of cognitive systems and
then
that organizes otherwise what would be
essentially arbitrary unlimited
information because the scope of
cognitive Sciences is so vast that
having a some of these categorizing
strategies a as part of our recall
system is part of it and then that's an
interesting question about jump starting
it and what do you bring
to zero what do you bring to the
table and then were the agents with our
tools that are building other agents and
tools and all of the like
reflexivity and also relevance that
comes along with
that yeah I like that
summary go on and on and on about I even
have different names for these things
but uh I want to there's a little bit of
Thunder I can't steal just yet uh but I
will ping you guys I I have a couple of
people in mind about sharing a
manuscript I've been working on for for
a many months at this point and uh it
this is related uh especially the
relationship between neurons the body
the environment and Beyond and how that
all ties together so this is stuff I've
been thinking a lot about so it's
actually timely your questions are great
I didn't know we'd get into this part
but uh you know that that's it's fun and
uh there's more to the story too there
there's other but I want to save that
Thunder yeah three maybe maybe you could
have me on about that paper if you ever
read that but uh you know that's a
different different thing 56 Never Dies
um exactly he doesn't leave leave us
alone or like a sequel like a one paper
a one paper sequel because I will say
like four four papers was was
challenging and I don't think we've
really like we we've skimmed the surface
of of each paper but like not even you
know there's there's so so many
interesting threads to untangle in just
what we've talked about here um and like
are you sure you don't want to go into
Evolution um are you sure I'm not
opposed to it I think the problem is
space source is
blue yeah no I I don't know that genetic
algorithms is necessarily like the the
way or the means like that that I mean
but I I really am curious about like
unraveling maybe alien cognition like
what does that look like when I really
start to think about like what is the
most different kind of cognition that I
could imagine what is the most different
from my own like I really think about
plant cognition and then like act of
inference becomes kind of problematic
because you know they they like they're
really limited they have a really
restricted like course of action right
um but but I think about like what you
know how how plants have evolved and how
they've co-evolved with humans like and
how they've you know they produce all
these lovely things that we like to eat
and they produce things that alter our
own cognition you know so so like they
can totally
drastically influence our information
transmission Pathways and and I I really
think about what does that cognitive
system look like or what is it like to
to be a plant or to have a memory that
looks like a plant memory right all of
your memory is essentially chemical like
or evolutionary and I think about that
in terms of like why like evolutionary
memory might be important um and across
species and across you know evolutionary
time like not necessarily evolving
through genetic algorithms but but what
does that evolutionary memory start to
look
like I mean it's a great question uh I
I've only I well I don't have any work
of my own well I have worked weirdly
enough with by the way I will say I have
worked with neuro
Evolution uh actually you guys had I
know you know the the ant colony paper
uh optimization with Abdul Ramen and
Travis right I was in the audience and I
chimed in and talk to about active
inference uh uh so I I have hedged my
bets a little bit you know to look at
other ways of doing things so I while I
did say I sold my soul to predictive
coding and common model of cognition
I guess it's not completely the truth
because I do look at other things but uh
so but I do think that it's interesting
blue that you bring up about things that
are not human or even maybe animal like
right because there's also animal
cognition which is there's some
differences um so when you go into
something like plant Evolution it's
interesting because there are there is
work as I have found again I I want to
say it in a way that again I don't steal
too much thund from this one paper I'm
like like it's on the tips of my tongue
you know and it's like I got no no hold
hold it's almost done I gotta finish the
edits put on archive and then we can all
chat about it um but there there is a
dressle of plant cognition and let's
like you said alien cognition or just
let's say non-human cognition and uh I
can this works existed it's wonderful
work to read have you guys heard of the
uh life mind continuity the thesis uh by
kirchof and others they're also heavily
influenced by Carl and free energy I
they might have even worked with him I I
sometimes because Carl's everywhere uh
but uh with with that in mind uh I like
the lifem continuity thesis because it
IT addresses a lot of things that have
emerged from evolutionary psychology
biology uh even like work that touches
in the world of Michael Levan's World
which car also worked a lot with uh and
uh these ideas that there is cognition
at the plant level or organism level you
can even go simpler like by the way
that's hard for me blue to imagine I've
been studying them uh not physically but
you know theoretically uh you know
bacterial organisms right or you know
even like eoli is a wonderful example of
studying Its Behavior it to also andise
is very
energy uh it opens the story to other
things which is also what inspires this
work that I've done very recently with
Carl that I keep teasing everyone about
but it's it is I promise it will come
out uh
but all of these things have cognition
but they are not cognitive in the way
that humans are so there's like and I've
long thought about this ever since uh I
was you know studying philosophy of Mind
as a young undergrad uh now of course
the the thing in when I was very young
was about Consciousness and
Consciousness
is very big world with a lot of
implications that I have to be careful
because there's been philosophical
theories forever and everyone has their
holes that they need to fill and then
there's flaws and I don't want to go
into like Thomas Sagel or dennit
concepts right now but um you know I
always thought well animals are
conscious and plants are conscious
they're just not conscious in the same
way there's degrees of Consciousness and
the reason I brought up the life mind
continuity thesis is that it sort of
talks about like gradations or degrees
of cognition and cognitive functionality
and as you go from because and I like
this premise I think it's an important
premise and since it's published work
from them I it's not like I'm stealing
any Thunder now it's already out there
and you guys even are nodding so I know
you know of it um you have the neurons
and nervous systems which evolved a lot
later in you know when you look at the
picture of life right and so what was
below that what are things that are more
foundational because other organisms
might not even have nervous systems and
yet they do beautifully complex things
they elicit beautifully complex Behavior
Uh even doing photosynthesis in a plant
is beautifully complex if you study the
details uh and it's you know it's also
an alien way of which they get their
nutrients right we don't do
photosynthesis uh you know and so it's a
completely different Evol evolved
behavior and so Michael Levan and other
researchers not just Michael but like
others have this thing called basil
cognition which is this really really
really low-level cognitive functionality
that emerges through the memory of
evolution so I agree with you blue you
can't completely ignore the role of
evolution in fact it's another piece to
the puzzle that you sort of have to
somehow account for and that's where the
life mind continuity thesis goes in the
opposite direction it says uh we have
highlevel cognition our complex minds
and brains we also have simple minds and
brains and it's not like all of the
sudden there's this hard discreet flip
switch where you say all of a sudden
there's a brain and then there's not a
brain it's like no plants do have a
brain just not the brain in which we
have a brain right and it's not a
nervous system it's you know these
evolved biological constructs that you
know have emerged from their primordial
biochemical soup of Evolution uh to then
allow them to for example uh manipulate
their structure in response to the
weather and rotate and move towards the
light right to better conduct
photosynthesis you know and their growth
mechanisms and so their very simple
Behavior obviously the plant's not going
to get up and walk and figure out oh I I
know I want to attack this other plant
right that's more high level Behavior
although we can come up with really cool
science fictions about it but um you
know that level of behavior is cognitive
it's just basil cognitive and so that
gives you what's called a simple mind or
even just a mind in a different part of
the spectrum and so how do we account
for that um I have some thoughts and I
don't want to steal that Thunder but
there's also the role of evolution they
talk about evolution in a life mind
continuity thesis and how you actually
can't get even the complex Minds to
emerge without a memory that is
evolutionary right so that's where you
have an Aggregate and so that leads you
and uh the engineer in me gets a little
uh anxious about this premise uh but not
because it's not the right path it's
rather my ability to contribute properly
to it uh because there's only so much
you can do which is well now you do have
to think in collectives right you can't
just model the individual anymore you do
have to have many IND individuals and
you need a population to then induce
some type of evolutionary process
because you need what kof and they say
in the Life mind continuity thesis is a
selection history you need the selection
history it can be through the
evolutionary process maybe there's other
ways to do it that they didn't say
specifically uh it's just what biology
does and that's what gives you the
submergent behavior right to create for
example the plant cognition that we
observe uh and of course you know the
very long chain that gave rise to the
evolution of you know apes and primates
and then the humans from that uh and so
you have that selection history so that
means we need to model populations in
you know the processes of which they
evolve um I the the reason I said the
engineering me gets anxious is it's
extremely my world complex to
computationally simulate just even one
agent so and when I do evolution and
I've done neuro Evolution you usually
simplify the little agents even the ant
colony the the paper that you guys
talked about well that was a really
beautiful example of emergence and other
really neat things uh those anti agents
that cans as my colleague talked to them
they're very simple they weren't even
neurals let alone a common imagine
running a thousand common model of
cognitions and that's not even enough to
do the evolution scale that we want so
that's where I I say oh um and again
knowing that that might limit what I
could do and researchers like me that go
on this pathway uh maybe the other
solution is okay well uh I'm just going
to figure out what the inductive biases
would have been that were evolved from
the evolution and I'll just skip the
evolutionary phase however that means
you could be wrong you could have gotten
the bias wrong right so you just say
well I need something so I'm gonna go
from there because I'm not given a
supercomputer to do the simulations that
I dream of doing I have a GPU you so I'm
going to build my little agent and I'll
and I'll just say when blue you
criticize it and you say well you know
that could be the right why is that the
right bias I'll say oh it's probably
wrong but you know it does give me these
behaviors you know so if we had the
right Behavior plug in my agent into
your simulation framework and I'd love
to see what happens so yeah and I'll
stop there so is this where sparsity
then comes in when it becomes like too
computationally intensive in terms of
like you know evolving a million little
tiny creatures or maybe this is a a a
good time to talk about
sparsity I mean oh first of all oh I see
you put a a link here in the chat I
didn't yeah yeah so if you want to see a
plant walk around watch the MIT so so
the MIT media lab has made the what's it
called L Len um anyway yeah if you want
to see the plant walk around I've shown
this before but they the plant will move
there's a little plant robot so wow okay
I have to read about this yeah it's
cool on the plant topic I I I brought in
these papers from 2017 with friston and
CVO on predictive processing in plants
and then uh paper from ' 89 with silver
town and Gordon making essentially the
exact same points in a broader
behavioral setting it's just like wave
after wave of the realization
that there are diverse intelligences
over different spatial and temporal
scales and the same things that people
remarked upon looking at a piece of
grass cracking up through the concrete
now is being instrumentally unified with
the most advanced cognitive modeling
that we have and and also Mike Levens
work certainly is to that point you made
a great point also about intelligence
accelerating Evolution and on Mike Len's
YouTube channel there's actually a
series of very good
discussions to that point um Evolution
trial by error and selection and pruning
and then Quantum intelligence basically
just teleporting you and getting to the
solution without needing to Traverse the
entire
landscape I'll read a question there's a
little bit of Chris Fields there too
right his Quantum and I know he and Carl
have been doing the quantum version of
free energy and marov blankets
yeah yeah and the course that Chris
provided at The Institute over the
previous months has
helped put a lot of things more in a
Quantum footing but that's a super
exciting Direction um I'll read a
question from the
chat can there be
self-regulation of ensembles of noisy
oracles without intelligence if so it
would be extremely helpful for a robot
mind so it can discount components that
are
malfunctioning okay so maybe repeat the
question one more time so I make sure
it's a little bit of a loaded
question it's so is aren't they all of
course yeah I think I need to parse it
repeat it one more times make sure I get
it right can there be self-regulation of
ensembles of noisy oracles without
intelligence
okay yeah the without intelligence part
is a little bit of a curve curve at the
end but can there be
ensembles engaging in distributed
regulation seems like yes that was the
sparsely connected hop field system that
you described so I think I think the key
I I wish the there could be a
clarification about Oracle right because
that's usually something you ask for an
answer right you know but I guess if
it's just to say oh it's like a sensory
reading or a hey I need to query this
part of myself right of my morphology or
my body and I need to understand what's
going on and I say hey tell me and you
give me the answer if I interpret it
that way and not maybe some other
interpretation uh yeah I would agree I
think I think our discussion has lend
itself to the implication that you want
ensembles I mean I I've said this
already are assemblies right I've said
even earlier when I was addressing some
comments for blue and uh vit's question
I believe was part of this piece about
how you implement memory um even just
even classical work on like
autoassociative and heter associative
memory back before even like talking
about hot field Nets like oh I have a
matrix and I can update it with some
heavy and learning and outer products of
vectors um and what I remember when I
was studying that is that they said well
you wouldn't use this one little Matrix
as the memory you would actually stitch
together an assembly of them right and
so that's how you get this complex
Behavior because you know even in
biology all the ranging up to nervous
systems to modules and structures in the
brain they are these like
self-organizing systems of parts and
relationships between those parts right
and we can interpret them as dynamical
systems and there's a lot of nice little
Frameworks we can apply um so the answer
to that or the general gist to that
question is yes you could build robotic
systems because I think that was the
kind of the application area um and
would you get things like fault
tolerance or would you get for example
if a part of the robots morphology or
body is damaged with that I think that
that would be the right design Paradigm
right that would be an appropriate
design Paradigm to construct it where
you have like a distributed form of
intelligence these uh you might not it
might the I think the nature of the
assembly might be important for example
it would probably be semih hierarchical
or heterarchical in nature uh Carl's
done some really nice uh theoretical
sketches of like uh Markov blankets of
Marco blankets which uh I I will just
borrow this question in that statement
to address a piece of something I forgot
to say to Blue in our earlier discussion
of the body and the niche and the
neurology or the neuron neuronal
constructs is the I also think it's
going to be important going forward to
embrace again there might there are
other ways to probably do this but I do
like the Markoff blanket formalism
because it partitions uh the states of
the outer world the internal States and
dynamics of the system which is very
vague but it leaves that on purpose and
then you have sensory and active States
as your blanket right your little Marco
blankie um and I think you need to
specify that uh and that will give you
the notion of like okay well there's the
theoretical body and then we need to
answer the question on how to physically
instantiate that so that was just a
quick thing I had in my notes I wanted
to make sure I didn't forget to say that
so I think that's another piece of that
puzzle you need to uh Embrace that and
then there's other Arguments for it but
that just something quickly and now that
goes back to the answer to the question
is that you would want to
construct uh you know a cognitive system
to manipulate the robot let's even leave
the common model and predictive coding
because those are just other tools that
you could use to construct your brain uh
but rather think of like the nervous
system of the robot and think of it as I
want a Markov blanket of Markov blankets
right uh and markco blank it's a Marco
blank and you can keep doing this
recursive nature where now you have your
little atomic unit and that markof
blanket kind of construct right is your
Oracle right it has its own internal
States and that map to some physical
component of the robot I think the part
is that now you are no longer just
saying I abstractly modeled the robot in
the software sense but it actually is
grounded in some physical component uh
Hardware property maybe a particular
piece of the robot and then you model
these with these little markof blankets
and then you have
macroscopic or a gradually increasing
macroscopic level markup blankets that
allow you to say well now I have this
organization but the internal states of
the higher level Marco blanket are you
know these other Marco blankets that
have their relationships and that goes
back to my biased background in complex
adaptive systems because what do you get
out of that you get what Herbert Simon
and some of the greats of our time you
know in the past you know talk about
heterarchical partially decomp posable
hierarchies right and you build these
beautiful complicated systems of control
right you have top- down modulation
because the upper level markof blankets
are maintaining their internal States
and there's dynamics that we should
probably figure out how to model that
I'm leaving the engineering side of this
out uh because that's an interesting
question of itself um and then those
Dynamics and those relationships and
laws between those higher level units
well they affect those lower level units
right because those lower level units
upwardly cause the emergence or the
existence of the internal states of the
upper level markup blanket but the rules
of the upper level Markoff blanket uh
downwardly cause this this is directions
of causation modulate and shape the
behavior and interactions of those lower
level modules so I think the answer is
yes you could do the uh assembly and the
noisy Oracle well noise is always a part
of it because you know for example
physics we always have a thermodynamic
exchange with our world there's always
loss of heat entropy must go up even if
we are an open system uh and the entropy
within us goes down the entropy of the
entire system of the niche and the agent
uh must go up because you can't violate
the second law of
Thermodynamics and I think that when you
consider that you're GNA have this and
you're also going to have in uh what do
you call it um imperfect sensors right
and you're going to have noisy sensors I
guess that's where the noisy Oracle
comes into play because you're not
always going to have a perfect reading
and you're going to have to make
decisions based on that that's where the
uncertainty part comes into play uh the
Precision waiting mechanisms of active
inference and free energy come into play
um and then how do those Dynamics change
when for example a part of my system
fails right I do think that that's a a
viable pathway or a design Paradigm for
constructing I would even not don't even
need to worry about the common model
part the nervous system right of the
robot do we just build you know that
complex interaction which is neuronal
right uh but we're using sort of that
hierarchy or the uh recursive Markov
blanket formulation to design this and
you can tell I like markof blankets
because they are a nice little entity
that tells you what's going on so I
don't know if that was a useful enough
answer to the question
but yeah great I I'll just note two key
pieces first in terms of what does free
energy principle and active inference
offer in alternative or in addition to
these other Frameworks a very clear
principled articulation between the math
and the theory and the implementation
which is already there in the common
framework but then to actually separate
out the discussion of how to structure
the Markov blankets and generative
models from the micro implementational
message passing on Factor graphs and
these features that can improve the
componentry as a capacity building work
while Blueprinting can be Blueprinting
rather than kind of needing to build the
blueprint on the ground which is always
going to end up with like an overly
bespoke setting and then also like even
when we are seemingly talk about a
single mind whatever an individual would
be we are really always talking about
the relationship with the niche the
multiple agents similar in different
types and the whole life cycle and then
you said that kind of like made you
nervous or something as an engineer
because it's like when you want to think
about engineering the car not not a car
engineer but one account would be to
focus on the car on the freeway driving
and everything working but then actually
the real systems engineering of the car
is the supply chain on through the
recycling and all the different ways
that it can interface with things that
are outside of the control and so to
just build a cognitive model that is
like in silico or just has this kind of
like inward perfect gaze it may be an
interesting project but then to engage
with the messiness of the
worlds that's where we again go back to
biology look at how it's done and then
try to accelerate or complement
it yep I mean we can learn a lot from
biology so H I think that's I think you
set it
well
um we could look a little bit to a paper
one of the maybe the
first blue you focused on the first
paper or h how about just what do you
see in figure two Alex how would you
describe figure two or if there's
another figure from this first paper
that you want to describe but just if
you whichever one you feel like is the
best graphical abstract just describe
how you see it I like figure two um
there's a couple other nice diagrams in
the paper I'm not
sure uh so I think this one is a nice
diagram I saw you guys go through this I
think everyone should watch0 zero
because I think you guys did a nice job
at least dissecting parts of it and some
mizing the the main takeaways um this is
just showing you this is now very fine
grain you know our discussion I don't
know if that was the intent or maybe
that's good thing I don't know how the
the podcast likes to keep things
constrained but uh we sort of went
really high level and then philosophical
mathematically conceptual uh and then
like you said we haven't really talked
about the papers but I would say this
paper in general is sort of like okay
given that discussion
now you're back to being the engineer
and saying okay where do I start what's
my Lego blocks if you play with Legos or
little toys and put things together to
build a tower I call this a Lego block
right this is a computational unit now
you could still go further as you guys
also did look at another paper called
spiking predictive coding I guess we'll
save that one for next we next session
um which is like the same thing it's
just really really uh intricate and that
would be what you'd put on neuromorphic
chips so this is like okay I want to
build a little Circuit of neurons and I
want them to relate to each other and
that's what like figure A1 is trying to
tell you it says that would be sort of
like your network in what's called
prediction mode and uh the idea is that
like the little two dots the gray dots
actually in general are what are called
State nodes or just the neuronal units
and the reason I call them State nodes
is is very different than deep learning
uh or at least most of deep learning
where these units always exist that's
kind of a this this goes back to maybe
the earlier part of our discussion uh
this paper is what I would call
mechanistic predictive coding right it's
saying I'm not just telling you the
principles of oh error and I bounc it
around and I somehow form Impressions
it's like okay how do I build this and
what would a neuronal model something
actually in your brain maybe a a little
group of like six neurons how would they
be related to each other or you know
maybe you're looking at it a little more
abstractly but uh this is supposed to
describe cortical structure specifically
but I like to think that this Paradigm
repeats itself and almost everywhere in
the brain there might be other ways of
doing things so in figure
A1 the little two dots the two cray
circles in Z2 those are just like okay I
have two neurons so I have little
regions and those are Layer Two then
there's these other two gray circles in
one called Z1 those are another set of
State neurons and then we have another
set of neurons z0 and that's at the
bottom so those are the actual physical
neurons and they exist all the time uh
and what I mean by that is that we
simulate their Dynamics this is why I
keep saying neural Dynamics is that
they're emulated through like an
ordinary differential equation right so
you have maybe an initial condition
which is just the number that you put
inside each one so these this model and
this paper still has some biological
constraints that oh they are modeling
roughly firing rates if you want to say
that uh so these are like rate coded
neurons uh my spiking implementation and
my my generalization of predictive
coding uh tries to say well maybe I'm
not interested in modeling Spike rats I
want to model the spike trains and this
is a stepping stone to that you actually
understanding this and understanding
those ordinary differential equations
that govern Z ofl which is like Z2 Z1 z0
um you kind of just modify them a little
bit and you outp spike trains which is
like really cool and uh and I have
slides that mention this a little bit
but maybe I'll use them next time since
we're we're you know we're going over
I'll just play off you guys and the the
material you have here and so Z2 and
A1 is
predicting Z1 and what do I mean by that
well Z2 I just told you has numbers
inside each of those gray circles right
it has at a particular snapshot in time
they have a firing rate right and it's
just represented by a number a scaler
and they emit a prediction using those
black diamond arrows that are like kind
of connecting to E1 we we'll talk about
E1 in a minute but those little black
diamond arrows and I have you know like
terminology for excitatory and
inhibitory neurons just to tell you oh
when do you subtract and when do you add
but let's just forget about the math
because if we get in the math that takes
a while and I've found confuses people
especially on these uh types of
presentations so just imagine those
scalar values inside of Z2 are being
transmitted along those black diamond
arrows down to Zar of one that's what
that little bar I think you can kind of
see it in your in your Visual and that's
the mean of a gausian distribution
because what the model that we're sort
of constructing is we're saying every
local set of neurons they are driving
like a car the uh car of a gan
multivariate gan distribution and so I
embrace uh more of a let's say a a
Frisian kind of view which is that we're
going to learn in this case somewhat of
a hierarchical gausian model and so Z2
makes a prediction of the mean and
that's what Zar one is in the paper and
you can see it in this diagram but it's
not like super clear there's also a
Precision Matrix or a covariance matrix
because a multivariate gan is defined by
a vector mean and then a square
symmetric Matrix for covariance you know
parameters and it's kind of like it lies
off to the side it's like lateral
connections really
and they are what those weird little
Diamond Open Diamond Connections in E1
are that's the Precision weights if you
will or the covariance weights um and so
between those you multiply the mean by
the Precision weights which is like a
lateral competition not even competition
it's more like a lateral pressure and
then you're done you've made a
prediction from Z2 to Z1 Z1 right I told
you has numbers inside of it right
because again these neurodynamics exist
at every snapshot in time so E1 is what
is known in mechanistic predictive
coding as the eror neurons and we we're
making other biological simplifications
we could discuss them later for there's
criticisms but uh Ean says okay I also
have two little diamonds these orange
diamonds and I need two of them right
because Z2 has to predict Z1 which has
two nodes so it needs to have a
dimensionality of two and I need one era
neuron to compare each Dimension so
there's a mapping of one to one there's
a biological criticism of that but for
computational purposes it's good so
we're going to go with it and Z1 each
Dimension is compared to each dimension
in Zar one and we can emulate this very
simply as in the paper you can take
derivatives of a free energy functional
uh but at the end of the day you do all
the math and it comes out to be a
subtraction Z1 minus Zar one that's it
so that's called a mismatch signal and
that's sort of emulating in a very very
simple way uh you know what what's known
as like The Superficial pyramidal cells
in your brain which sometimes are argued
to do like these mismatch computations
uh that's kind of one one interpretation
of them and the idea make sure that I
actually wrote that down make sure I
didn't get that
flipped yeah no I'm right yeah yeah the
superficial and then the the state neur
ODS are what are called Deep excitatory
pyramidal cells so these are you could
almost argue I'm using a lot of
pyramidal cells but they're just
neuronal units uh that's just the bio
interpretation and that's pretty much it
so E1 Compares zbar One to Z1 and now
you just repeat right so Z1 would be
guessing the activity of z0 which means
it emulates z bar R of Zer which is the
mean of the gausian of the layer below
and you know you'll have a Precision
Matrix you'll have a set of eror neurons
but the calculation just repeats and
that's pretty much it you have now a
canonical predictive coding circuit um
this the the interesting piece of this
is this is very similar to like regish
Rous model uh except it's not applied to
image patches it's just applied to sort
of the vector space directly um that's
what parentheses one is it's like the
prediction mode and then A2 says okay
you made those predictions by the way Z1
sorry Z2 predicting Z1 is made in
parallel which is a beautiful property
that I want to emphasize right now to Z1
predicting z0 by the way z0 in this case
you would clamp those numbers to a data
point so for example like I do in this
paper and I know you and talked about it
last time uh pixels of an image right um
and maybe by the way you can change the
distribution I will add a quick caveat
that the bottom layer is actually a
multivariate bermi distribution because
I'm modeling binary pixels but it
doesn't really matter just pretend
everything's gausian because it's easy
to visualize for the audience um and so
that's prediction mode those things
happen in parallel notice that the
prediction z0 bar does not depend on any
except Z1 so for free you get something
that's already brain likee which is a
kind of answering a question I know you
and bluee head about like what do I get
from this right what do I get it's kind
of like what do I what does predictive
coding bring to the table you get
layerwise parallelism for free and
that's a really nice property because if
you can you know emulate that you have
multiple gpus or CPUs you have a a
performance cluster uh you know you
could now actually do literal parallel
ISM whereas deep learning you have to
kind of like run a for propagation pass
everything is locked into sequence this
is parallel now the problem with that is
now you have to do message passing which
I know you guys are familiar with it so
I don't need to maybe go into so much
detail but that's what two is it tells
you how to take the messages at E1 and
EZ which are error messages right they
tell you how far off was the prediction
made to the thing I wanted to look at
and then I backwards transmit that
information along a different set of
synapses which is sort of what makes
neurogenerative coding a little bit
unique uh we talk about this in my
survey as well uh compared to Rish ral's
model and even Carl's older models uh
which are essentially you would just
take the transpose of the weight Matrix
for Ford uh prediction uh but that's not
biological because we don't don't reuse
synapses there is no evidence of the
weight transport problem which is I go
back along the weights that I
transmitted for it the brain is really
recurrent uh and so I embrac that uh and
so you have a different set of synapses
you can call them feedback if you want
but I call them error synapses it
doesn't matter and that's what those
little diamond or sorry dashed open
circle uh lines are doing is they are
taking the little diamonds uh the orange
diamond values and they are backwards
transmitting them to a particular layer
and it's usually back to the state
neurons that made the original
prediction and then the last piece of
the puzzle if you just want to
understand why are what are those uh
dashed solid diamond ones well those
aren't actually synapses they could be
uh they are just basically oh let me
take the era message and let me subtract
it and this is how you get top down
pressure because you need to have bottom
up top down pressures at every layer of
neurons and so this is where that
message passing happens that one step
right now I've only shown you one step
Z1S Dynamics are going to be
perturbed by the message that was passed
from the layer below so in this case for
Z1 it's the message from
e0 and then the prediction or the
reverse of the prediction of layer Z2
which is the minus E1 and that's what I
have the equations in the paper and I
could show some slides that walk you
through these steps if you want maybe
next time uh but uh the idea is that
that happens at Z1 by the way all the
layers of neurons do this as long as
they're not clamped to data because if
you clamp them that means you fix them
to a set of values that you're saying
well I know what the data is I don't
need to infer it so I'm going to put it
here um so that's z0 in this case would
always be pixels of an image maybe they
change with time but but let's keep it
static and then all you do is you repeat
step one and step two multiple times
right until you reach a a a steady state
which is one thing you could do which is
how many times do you repeat that well
you reach equilibrium or you just bound
it and you say I'm gonna run this for
like I do in the paper a number K you
know 10 steps right and what is this
doing is it's changing the values inside
of Z1 and Z2 only notice I've said
nothing about synapses the synapses are
just whatever numbers they are the
synaptic strengths are fixed at this
point so let's say I reach a steady
state or I do this for like K times then
you make an update to all the synapses
so the four the solid uh do uh solid
diamond arrows which were the the
generative weights and the dashed open
circle synapses those are put inside
matrices and you just calculate their
updates with heavan learning right it's
really easy I have statistics paper
shows you those rules it's just a matter
of product um what is this doing well
you probably are familiar with like
Dynamic expectation maximization from
none other than Carl right and
generalized filtering it's a form of
that it's just a
biological uh manifestation of dynamic
em uh in this specific context um when
you do things at the spiking level you
don't need to wait so long to do
synaptic plasticity updates uh I do
those online that means Every Step in
Time synapses change and you write out
their ordinary differential equation we
can save that for I think that is
actually supposed to be for next time so
we can dive into that fun pile of uh
Dynamics later and that's pretty much it
I mean the little diagram B is just
trying to show you oh what do the cells
look like so if I just zoom in on like
two uh one single state node and one
single eror neuron cell you're looking
at scalers right and I'm just saying
well this is how they wire together and
then the so that's just a zoom in if you
want if you will if you don't like
matrices because Engineers we love
vectors and matrices and vectorizing
because you can run them on a GPU uh but
uh the oldfashioned way in the 80s was
scalers and then on the right uh we have
diagram C and that's actually showing
you all four models that we investigated
in that journal article and it's cool
because this paper's long by the way so
it's funny um I admire you guys for
doing four of my papers and on top of
them they weren't short little guys
either um this paper has a very long
appendix I don't know if you found the
supplementary material uh that was the
reviewers I they had us do a lot of
extra things um the appendix actually
tells you a lot uh and among the things
that it does is it emphasizes something
that I think the message kind of got a
little tiny bit muted in the main
article but that's just how nature is it
wants you to sort of say Give me the
main thing show me the results all the
beautiful math box it up in this nice
little corner and if people really care
they'll look at it um and so the diagram
to the right emphasizes something that
in the appendix talks about a naming
convention so neurogenerative coding
isn't just predictive coding it's like a
computational framework that tries to
unify as much of predictive coding as I
felt that I could in the paper and so
that's why the model has underneath
there GN cnt1 in the appendix there's
like a section that tells you how to
interpret why do I use the word
gncn what is T1 it means type one T2
means type two and those were refer to
the error synapses because you'll see
Ral regish ral's name in the model there
at the bottom and that's to pay homage
because you know I'm a I'm a big buff
for historical research and I like to
pay credit whereas a lot of people don't
uh to Old work because we stand on the
shoulders of giants and so as I told you
I read a lot of Rouse's work um that
model is named after him because it is
effectively like the fully connected
version of his patch model in his
classical nature paper and that is a
neural generative coding Network under
specific assumptions and so like any
mathematici you just say oh I recover
this older model because it's a subset
of my theory uh and then uh the middle
the second
model usually it's a little bit similar
to regish ral's it's essentially Carl's
model from is either 2008 or 2010 uh the
reviewers wanted us to implement that
and it's not a model mod that many
people I hate to say Implement besides
Carl so I had to do that and uh it was
fun and basically it's just a large
piece of it is making sure you get those
Precision matrices right because he
introduces that in one of his like
graphical model papers and so that's why
it's named after him uh that pays homage
to his classical work and then the uh
two to the right are the new models and
that's the ones that like for example
have separate feedback synapses which is
not something that older models directly
addressed Carl has mentioned them but he
at least the mathematics or the models
that of those papers did not concretely
tell you how to implement them let alone
how to learn them so all of my models
all my synapses are learned with like
heavan like plasticity and then the last
Model the farthest one to the right the
reason I like the reason I'm spending
time on these is because those are the
core models we looked at in the paper
the one to the far right just says oh
well because NGC is such a broad
framework you are not committed to a
hierarchical model you could build a
heterarchical model or a weird model
that has skip connections right and so
that's why you see this like weird Arrow
going from the very very top layer all
the way down to the bottom and so the
math in the paper shows you oh I can
turn off with these little gating
variables uh these weird kind of skip
connections that violate the hierarchy
but you can still learn them in heavy
and ways so the efficiency is all there
it turns out that model actually worked
the best and so uh there are you guys
actually showed in 0 Z the the data
samples and those are what I Ed I use
the final model the gncn pdh that's like
a little compression because when you
use a a naming convention the names get
really long to a certain point so you're
just like well I'm not going to say gncn
T2 L Sigma which refers to the lateral
connections and the C and the Precision
weights and PD I'll just call it pdh
right you can just say that to your
friends and it's quick and rolls off the
tongue um so that that's a little weird
naming thing I did and so the nice thing
about these models is they they do show
you pretty much all the mechanics uh at
least visually and then the other piece
to this puzzle is you'll notice those
gray circles back in figure a also have
synapses that I didn't really address
those are lateral synapses at the state
node level which is also something that
you know you know classical work like
Rous and friston's models and others
don't really use this is something we
introduced which encourages like what I
would argue extreme sparsity and the
motivation for that because I know blue
had a question or just wanted to chat a
little bit about sparsity so maybe this
is a way I'll sneak it in is that uh
raal for example introduced sparsity by
imposing a CTIC plasan prior which just
is basically a pointy distribution over
the neural firing rates that just say I
want some of these neurons to go to zero
and other ones to be high and I want you
know as many of them to be zero as
possible and that's a useful way to do
sparsity it actually comes from Bruno
Howen and sparse coding work and I cite
Bruno I've met Bruno Howen too he's a
cool guy uh you know you can get these
activities to be really really really
sparse so most of them are zero because
zero why do we care about zero not just
from a biological Point of View Hardware
loves zero zero means I don't compute it
so if I don't have to compute it I don't
use any hardware resources for it I can
ignore it um it's those numbers that
aren't zero that are annoying for a
computer and so instead of doing a llan
prior which I did investigate in this
paper and I think I even have the
Dynamics in there as well it's like one
of the equations um and to be faithful
to Ral uh reesh I had to put that in
there um but uh the lateral K synaptic
connections the state nodes what they do
is you uh what we did in this one is we
introduced fixed weights because that's
the easiest thing to do you don't have
to learn them later on I've learned them
that's like some future work um and what
these these lateral synapses do is they
have a it's like a a matrix and they are
shaped to be a square uh and they're
like let's say the dimensionality of a
layer so in the top layer be 2 cross two
along the main diagonal are a set of
positive numbers or or maybe negative
numbers you have to be you have to make
sure that the middle diagonal is
excitatory and it's called self
excitatory which means if a single
neuron Fires at a Step in Time its new
firing rate is going to be Amplified by
its own firing rate so that's called
self excitatory or self
exitation and the off Di diagonal so the
lower and upper right triangle of this
lateral Matrix that I'm talking to you
about that has to be the opposite sign
so I would believe it would be negative
unless you wrote the negative sign in
the OD then it changes and those are
negative numbers and the idea is that
those down put a downward pressure and
says this neuron let's say in this one
element of the column will laterally
inhibit other neurons in that layer and
the cool part and again it's in the
super long appendix of that paper you
can find it um that Matrix even though I
fix it because I didn't you could try to
learn it with like heavy and learning
and I later like investigated that um
you what you might say okay I'll put
some random numbers in that Matrix but
wait a minute do I really want every
neuron in the main diagonal to inhibit
all the other neurons the answer is
probably not you could that is a type of
pattern what I did is I initialize a
masking Matrix and in that Matrix
without going into the details of that
because it's there's a little bit of an
algorithm it just basically says little
groups of neurons inhibit each other and
no and no one else and so you basically
turn off things in that Matrix you fix
it with a mask and now you get group
sparcity and so the long story short
with all of that cool description is
that you get K winner take all type uh
lateral competition but it's
biologically implemented so I'm not like
using an activation function and as you
go through the Dynamics of this model
this Matrix what it'll do is it'll
emphasize neurons that are really
important for the object that you're
processing and it will shut up all the
other neurons that aren't relevant right
and so this is uh to answer a question I
believe it was blue uh in you Daniel we
discussing last last week about the
results that we had in this paper uh
because it's not shown here in this
diagram but the idea is that we also got
really good classification performance
this model has no label right so we
trained like a little probe or whatever
on the topmost layer and we also showed
some TSN plots and the reason I think
that the model works as well as it does
for something it wasn't trained to do
which is discrete categorization of
object category like different numbers
like the digit zeros the zero category
is because of that sparsity and we did
measure the sparsity levels and they
were really really really tiny the
proportion of neurons that were active
as you go through these Dynamics
especially as it learned is it said oh I
don't need a lot of neurons to represent
zero so it sort of like extracted out
little sub networks that specialize to
these templates right so I don't we
didn't we didn't exactly probe that
hypothesis but that's what I speculate
is going on uh and it's also very easy
you can justify it uh from the past you
can say sparcity is a really important
way to do uh memory retrieval it's a
beautiful way to fight catastrophic
forgetting which is another piece of my
work that tries to look at that and the
idea is that you're going to get
nonoverlapping
representations right so you know if we
only have a few neurons and a sparse
distributed memory semantically if these
units activate they're probably related
to roughly the same concept and you'll
learn as long as you have big enough
layers of course this is the thing where
you do need like brain level stuff you
need lots of neurons uh you'll find that
they don't cross talk with each other
they don't fight each other so much so
knowledge for zero doesn't fight with
the knowledge of Two And so you'll have
this nice beautiful separation and I
think it makes things like
classification a little bit easy here
it's really nice for fighting forgetting
because you'll remember things a lot
more until eventually run out of
capacity and then you just need more
neurons um and it's also energy
efficient so the big big argument is if
everything is zero except for like a few
neurons firing that's a perfect
candidate for neuromorphic computing um
and then if we can make them Spike which
is what the other paper you guys review
tried to do uh then we solve all of
those weird things because you should
only be communicating with
you shouldn't be communicating with uh
rate coded continuous values which are
clean but they're not good for Hardware
like a neuromorphic chip or a Meister so
that's kind of the general gist of it
and I I think uh that's where you get
this beautiful benefit of sparsity and
you see this nice interaction and you're
learning a generative model and of
course that paper actually synthesizes
the models we look at what samples are
produced um yeah and I could keep going
on and on but hopefully that that was
useful and made sense I see blue is gone
so maybe I I I got boring
here that
was great and a
lot yeah it was a
lot what do you did make
sense it helped me it helped me even
after reading all the papers multiple
times hearing this explanation still
really did help I hope it's helpful for
other people too um there's an enormous
amount of
condensation but you really are laying
it out like an
engineer how do we build the three-story
building what's the wiring diagram of
each floor and then you're clearly um
striking a fine balance with how much of
the
mathematics to visually
convey versus Explore her and that's why
there's appendices that's why there's
sequences of
papers um what are you looking forward
to in dot two or just as we kind of
close out yeah I don't know if we went
too long I'm sorry if much uh well I
mean I'm looking forward to continuing
some of this discussion I think uh we
didn't really even touch on the
convolutional one which is really you
could even argue as more of a a to use
Carl's terms you could think of it as
the convolutional neural coding is a
corollary to the neural generative
coding framework because it just says
wait a minute how do I do image
processing in an efficient way um let's
do deconvolution or convolution that
could be something we briefly touch on
next time I'm looking forward to the
spiking stuff because I really really
love spiking neuronal cells and I don't
think he was able to make it but one of
my students works with me on Spike time
in and uh synaptic plasticity that's
driven through solely spikes um so I you
know have a particular soft spot for
that and I think the future predictive
coding at least where I'm trying to lead
the crowd is to do things at the spike
level because neuromorphic Computing
offers beautiful Energy Efficiency we
could do Edge Computing so I'm looking
forward to some of that chat I also love
we sort of borrowed big chunk of what I
think you wanted Daniel us to do with
the cognitive architecture because we
kind of brought all that today I know
blue is very interested in that so we
sort of front-loaded with a lot of that
um so I was gonna say I'm looking
forward to that but I I mean I'm always
looking forward to chatting more uh I
think we front loaded it so maybe we
could address more the predictive coding
pieces however I do have slides that
I'll probably share if you want me to um
that maybe talk about other aspects of
the cognitive architecture that aren't
just the Cog engine but rather like oh
I'll show you something I did in
robotics uh in a paper at icra this year
I could show you some things about how
you can make predictive coding do
something a little bit more concretely
active inference without obscuring it
with the common model because I think
the common model is like you get kind of
lost not you but the audience in general
might say oh all these continents of
mind and how do they relate well wait
where's the active in and I I talk about
there it's in there uh I think sometimes
it's good to say Let me throw away all
that for just a minute because memory
can kind of cloud it let's just look at
epistemic foraging and prior preference
and maybe do something simple like have
a robot arm manipulated uh manipulate an
object and we could I could talk about
that um and also just chatting more
about like the future of this I I think
that this is I I think
what I am trying to represent and
actually with dis a lot of discussion
with Carl I think I've narrowed down
what I what I bring to the table to the
fields of cognitive science
computational neuroscience and machine
learning which is the three the Triad
that my lab represents um is this thing
called biomimetic intelligence and I
think that we need to understand the
neurophysiology the bi ology of things
and also understand the physics of
things and understand how the niche and
the body and the neuronal constructs all
interplay together to then build
technological artifacts that do things
like robotics at in an an energy
efficient way um and I think this is
that path this is one possible Pathway
to AGI uh I think it's the path but uh
I'm obviously could be clearly wrong uh
you know we all don't know until we get
there and we have perfect hindsight but
I think that that could be a fun little
bit of discussion because I know you
guys were interested in knowing about
the future work that my team has been
trying to do as well as the history of
those papers which I didn't get to talk
about I know blue had said something she
was interested to know what was the
order of these papers and I had this in
my notes so we can we can save those for
the next session if you guys want to
talk about them or other questions I'm
open to anything really
awesome yeah this was
huge it really it's a tour to force of
cognitive science and engineering so I
hope the people enjoyed it looking
forward to talking next week if you're
watching one now and you want to join
next week this may be possible and
thanks again see you and thank you thank
you for having me we appreciate it see
you bye take care